Guide to the Walter A. Fairservis Papers, 1931-1994
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Walter A. Fairservis Papers
1931-1994
Fairservis, Walter Ashlin, 1921-1994
10 cubic feet (10 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Correspondence, manuscripts, teaching materials, publications, and other papers related to Fairservis's work as a professor, archaeologist, author, and playwright. Of particular note is his correspondence with his family describing his trips overseas.
Biographical Note
Walter Ashlin Fairservis, Jr. (1921-1994) was an American archaeologist, professor, author, and playwright. Born in Brooklyn, N.Y. to Walter A. Fairservis and actress Edith Yeager, Fairservis traveled the country with his mother and worked as a child actor and peformer. During the Second World War, Fairservis served as a lieutenant in Army Intelligence and served in Japan as a member of General Douglas MacArthur's occupation staff. After the war, Fairservis attended Columbia University, where he received both his B.A. and M.A. degrees. He began his archaelogical work with American Museum of Natural History in 1949 on an expedition to the Quetta Valley in Pakistan. He went on to director a number of other expeditions, and received his Ph.D. from Harvard University.
Fairservis joined the Vassar College faculty in 1969 as professor of anthropology. Before his retirement in 1993, he would serve as both Chair of the Anthropology Department and Director of the Asian Studies Program. In 1983, he founded the nonprofit East-West Fusion Theater in his home of Sharon, CT. His wife, Jan (Sutherland) Fairservis, was an artist and illustrator.
He died in 1994, at the age of 73.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, teaching materials, and other papers related to Fairservis's work as a professor, archaeologist, author, and playwright. Of particular note is his correspondence with his family describing his trips overseas. Also of note is the material relating to his training in Japanese language and culture for the military, as well as the correspondence from Hoyt Van Buren to Jan Fairservis while he was training for the U.S. Army Air Force.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
The Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology at Harvard University holds a collection of Fairservis's archaeological research materials.
The Penn Museum Archives at the University of Pennsylvania also hold a small collection of Fairservis's papers.
Vassar College Anthropology Department Records
Subject Headings
Names:
Fairservis, Jan
Organizations:
Military Intelligence Service Language School (U.S.); American Museum of Natural History; United States. War Department. Military Intelligence Service. Pacific Unit; Vassar College--Faculty
Subjects:
Anthropologists; Anthropology--Study and teaching; Archaeologists; Archaeology--Study and teaching; Theater—Japan; World War, 1939-1945—Japan
Places:
Afghanistan--Description and travel; Pakistan--Description and travel
Document Types:
Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Notebooks; Photographs; Printed ephemera
VCL Categories:
Anthropology and Anthropologists; East Asia, South Asia, and India; Theater, Drama and Film; Travel; Vassar College; War and War Crimes
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, December 2009.
Updated by Emma Gronbeck, November 2025.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection was the gift of Jan Fairservis to Vassar College in 2005 (M2006-019). Other materials were transferred from the Peabody Museum in 2007 (M2007-006) after being separated from their collection, which was a 2004 gift of Jan Fairservis. Some materials from this accession were later returned to the Peabody Museum in 2010.
The videotapes were of gift of Teviot Fairservis (M2011-016).
Arrangement
This collection has not been fully processed. If research proves difficult at the current level of processing, arrangements may be made to provide further arrangement and description work for the collection.
Series List
- Series I. Biographical Material, 1931-1982; (Boxes 1 and 8)
- Series II. Correspondence, 1939-1992; (Boxes 1-2)
- Series III. Teaching Material, 1968-1989; (Boxes 3 and 8)
- Series IV. Writings and Research, 1994, undated; (Boxes 3-4 and 8)
- Series V. Drama and Theater, undated; (Boxes 4-6 and 8-10)
- Series VI. Edith Yeager Papers, undated; (Box 6)
- Series VII. Japanese Work for the U.S. Military, 1944-1947; (Box 7)
Container List
- SERIES I. Biographical Material, 1939-1992
  - Genealogy (Folder 1.1)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — General (Folder 1.2)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Clippings (Folder 1.3)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Track in U.S. Army, 1945-1946 (Folder 1.4)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Michigan Track Team, 1944-1945 (Folder 1.5)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Athletics (Folders 1.6-1.7)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Trip on the Mauretania, 1931 (Folder 1.8)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Mt. Vernon High School Hall of Fame, 1982 (Folder 1.9)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Columbia diploma (Box 8)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. — Miscellaneous (Folder 1.10)
  - Fairservis, Jan (Folders 1.11-1.12)
  - Fairservis Family — House Plans (Folders 1.13-1.14)
  - Fairservis Family — Christmas Cards (Folder 1.15)
  - Fairservis Family — Miscellaneous (Folders 1.16-1.20)
  - Ephemera (Folder 1.21)
  - Photographs (Folder 8.18)
  - Undeveloped film (Box 8)
- SERIES II. Correspondence, 1939-1992
  - Fairservis, Walter A. to Fairservis, Jan, 1947-1976, undated (Folders 1.22-1.26)
  - Fairservis, Jan to Fairservis, Walter A., 1947-1948 (Folders 1.27-1.28)
  - Fairservis, Jan to Fairservis, Walter A., 1949-1964, undated (Folder 2.1)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. to Yeager, Edith, circa 1939 - 1946, undated (Folders 2.2-2.5)
  - Yeager, Edith to Fairservis, Walter A., 1941-1955, undated (Folders 2.6-2.7)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Fairservis, Walter A. to Fairservis, Jan, 1949 (Folder 2.8)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Fairservis, Jan to Fairservis, Walter A., 1949 (Folder 2.9)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Fairservis, Jan to Family, 1950 - 1951 (Folder 2.10)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Family to Fairservis, Jan and Walter A., 1950 - 1951 (Folder 2.11)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Yeager, Edith to Fairservis, Walter A., 1949 - 1951 (Folder 2.12)
  - Afghanistan / Pakistan Trip — Miscellaneous correspondence and other items, 1949 - 1951 (Folder 2.13)
  - Miscellaneous friends and family to Fairservis, Walter A., 1936 - 1982 (Folders 2.14-2.16)
  - Miscellaneous friends and family to Fairservis, Jan (Folder 2.17)
  - Miscellaneous friends and family to Fairservis, Jan and Walter A. (Folder 2.18)
  - Fairservis, Jan to family (Folder 2.19)
  - The Sutherland Family (Folder 2.20)
  - Fairservis children — to and from (Folder 2.21)
  - Van Buren, Hoyt to Fairservis, Jan, 1943-1946 (Folders 2.22-2.23)
  - Fairservis, Walter A. to Miscellaneous (Folder 2.24)
  - U.S. Army (Folder 2.25)
  - Miscellaneous Professional — Fairservis, Walter A. (Folder 2.21)
  - Miscellaneous Professional — Fairservis, Jan (Folder 3.1)
  - Benton, William, 1963-1964 (Folder 3.2)
  - O'Donnell, C. Donald (Folder 3.3)
  - Lewin, Albert, 1959-1966 (Folder 3.4)
  - Yeager, Edith - Miscellaneous (Folder 3.5)
  - "Aunt Norma" to Yeager, Edith (Folder 3.6)
  - Poultny Bigelow to Yeager, Edith, 1945-1952 (Folder 3.7)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 3.8)
  - Transcripts of WWII letters of Brent Winn, sent to Walter A. Fairservis by Janette Winn, 1992 (Folder 3.9)
- SERIES III. Teaching Material, 1968-1989
  - Vassar College — Correspondence (Folders 3.10-3.11)
  - Vassar College — Course Material (Folders 3.12-3.15)
  - Vassar College — Course Material (Folder 8.17)
  - Vassar College — "Projects for Beginning Classes" (Folder 3.16)
  - Vassar College — Chinese Program Annual Reports, 1968-1989 (Folder 3.17)
  - Vassar College — Miscellaneous (Folders 3.18-3.19)
  - New York University (Folder 3.20)
  - University of Washington (Folder 3.21)
  - Correspondence from Students (Folder 3.22)
- SERIES IV. Writings and Research, 1994, undated
  - "America vs. the United States" (Folder 3.23)
  - "The American Museum of Natural History and I" (Folder 3.24)
  - "Barre, A Community in Photographs" (Folders 3.25-3.29)
  - Black Glaze Analysis (Folder 3.30)
  - "Education in the United States,", 1994 (Folder 4.1)
  - Education, Reading and Writing project (Folders 4.2-4.3)
  - "Collections of children's drawings and early writing examples..." (Folders 4.4-4.5)
  - "Fever" (Folder 4.6)
  - "Josiah" (poem) (Folder 4.7)
  - "The Lamp of Ghazni - Ala Al-Din (Folder 8.1)
  - Letters to newspapers (Folder 4.8)
  - "The Lion" (Folder 4.9)
  - "Netsuke" (Folder 4.10)
  - "New Ways in the New World," with Jan Fairservis (Folder 4.11)
  - "Once We Laughed Together" (Folder 4.12)
  - Review of Possehl book (Folder 4.13)
  - "The Savior of Kyoto" (Folder 8.2)
  - "Tales out of Hell and Heaven" (Folder 4.14)
  - The theatre and archaeology (Folder 4.15)
  - "Voices of Veterans" (Folder 4.16)
  - "Wage Peace" (Folder 4.17)
  - Notes on ritual and drama (Folder 4.18)
  - Unidentified manuscript (Folder 4.19)
  - Unidentified manuscript (Folder 8.3)
  - Class notes [?] (Folder 4.20)
  - W.A.F.'s library (Folder 4.21)
  - Childhood writings and school material (Folder 4.22)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 4.23)
- SERIES V. Drama and Theater, undated
  - Plays — "Baseball Noh" (Folder 4.24)
  - Plays — "Drums at Yale (Folder 4.25)
  - Plays — "Edith" (Folders 4.26-4.29)
  - Plays — "Forgotten Spirit" (Folders 4.30-4.31)
  - Plays — "Forgotten Spirit" (Folders 5.1-5.7)
  - Plays — "The Great Goddess and the Nine Wonders" (Folder 8.4)
  - Plays — "The History of the United States..." (Folder 5.8)
  - Plays — "The History of the United States..." (Folder 8.5)
  - Plays — "The House of [ ? ]" (Folder 8.6)
  - Plays — Ikari notes (Folder 5.9)
  - Plays — "Josiah" (Folder 8.7)
  - Plays — "Kichibi" (Folder 5.10)
  - Plays — "The Last Pipes of Arcady" (Folders 5.11-5.14)
  - Plays — "The Last Pipes of Arcady" (Folder 8.8)
  - Plays — "Manifest Destiny" (Folders 5.15-5.16)
  - Plays — "Mikayo" (Folder 5.17)
  - Plays — "Nathan Hale" (Folders 5.18-5.20)
  - Plays — "Polo Grounds" (Folder 5.21)
  - Plays — "Saul" (Folder 8.9)
  - Plays — "Snake Story" (Folders 8.10-8.11)
  - Plays — "The Sword of Tamerlane" (Folder 5.22)
  - Plays — "Wagon Train West" (Folder 8.12)
  - Plays — "Yamashita, Yamashita" (Folder 5.23)
  - Plays — "Voices of Veterans" (Folder 5.24)
  - Plays — "The Way of the World" (Folder 5.25)
  - Plays — Miscellaneous (Folder 5.26)
  - Plays — Miscellaneous notes (Folder 5.35)
  - Plays — Unidentified (Folders 5.27-5.28)
  - Plays — Unidentified (Folder 8.13)
  - Plays — Miscellaneous playbills (Folder 5.29)
  - Plays — Miscellaneous notes (Folder 6.4)
  - Plays — Miscellaneous notes (Folders 8.14-8.15)
  - Plays — Copyright certificates (Folder 6.5)
  - BBC TV — "Buried Treasure" (Folder 5.30)
  - Miscellaneous CBS productions (Folder 5.31)
  - CBS TV — "Man in the Mist" (Folder 5.32)
  - CBS TV — "Adventure" (Folders 5.33-5.34)
  - Radio — "The Second Hand" (Folder 5.36)
  - Radio — Audition pieces (Folder 6.1)
  - Radio? — "The Big Story" (Folder 6.2)
  - Radio? — "The Last of the Samuels" (Folder 6.3)
  - A.C.T. (Folder 6.6)
  - Actors studio (Folder 6.7)
  - Arnold, Benedict (Folder 6.8)
  - Asian Theatre Journal (Folder 6.9)
  - Breese, Gerald (Folder 6.10)
  - Calabro, Tony (Folder 6.11)
  - Center Spot Players (Folder 6.12)
  - Dramatic Publishing Co. (Folder 6.13)
  - Drama — Critic's Notices (Folder 6.14)
  - East-West Fusion Theatre (Folder 6.15)
  - Freydberg, J. (Folder 6.16)
  - Gam, Rita (Folder 6.17)
  - Ideas — Plays (Folder 6.18)
  - Ikaki (Folder 6.19)
  - Janney, Ben (Folder 6.20)
  - Lewis, Lester (Folder 6.21)
  - Long Island University Theatre (Folder 6.22)
  - Martin, Elliot (Folder 6.23)
  - Miller, Arthur (Folder 6.24)
  - Nakemura, Masami (Folder 6.25)
  - Opera acting (Folder 6.26)
  - Pan-Asian Rep. (Folder 6.27)
  - Parlakian, Nishan (Folder 6.28)
  - Philips, Jud (Folder 6.29)
  - The Pyramid (Folder 6.30)
  - Seattle Repertory Theatre (Folder 6.31)
  - Sharon Playhouse (Folder 6.32)
  - Stage Design — Jan Fairservis (Folder 6.33)
  - Straight Wharf Theatre — 1951 season (Folder 8.16)
  - Taylor, Clyde (Folder 6.34)
  - Theatre — Religious (Folder 6.35)
  - Theatre — Sides and scenes (Folder 6.36)
  - Theatre Northwest (Folder 6.37)
  - Theatre One (Folder 6.38)
  - Vassar Theatre (Folder 6.39)
  - The Wasp (Folder 6.40)
  - Westchester County Civic Opera (Folder 6.41)
  - Williams, Annie-Laurie (Folder 6.42)
  - Copyrights (Folder 6.42)
  - Correspondence — Miscellaneous theatre-related (Folder 6.42)
  - Videotapes of various performances (Boxes 9-10)
- SERIES VI. Edith Yeager Material, undated
  - 2 notebooks of Yeager writings (Box 6)
  - Yeager writings, including documents from her YMCA service in France in WWI (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Yeager material (Box 6)
- SERIES VII. Japanese Work for the U.S. Military, 1944-1947
  - Ken Edge — Book, thoughts on Japan, 1947 (Box 7)
  - Letters and printed ephemera collected while stationed in Tokyo, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Materials from Military Intelligence School, Minneapolis, including modern conversational Japanese exercises and interrogation tests, 1944 (Box 7)
  - Notebooks and other materials from Japanese language course, University of Michigan, 1944 (Box 7)
  - Official indictment against Japan and Japanese individuals, International Tribunal Against the Far East, 1945 (Box 7)
  - Political writings in Japanese, circa 1944 (Box 7)
  - "Propaganda for Japanese Consumption," prepared by MISLS, Fort Snelling, MN, 1945 Apr (Box 7)
  - "Reproduction of a Captured Japanese Diary," Military Intelligence Service Language School, Fort Snelling, Minnesota, 1945 Jul 11 (Box 7)
  - Russian interrogation of Japanese, 1946 (Box 7)